Benjamin Franklin Papers Part 7 -- Letters to Franklin 1783 January-November Mss.B.F85inventory07
American Philosophical Society
- Letters to Benjamin Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 October 20; A.L.S. 2p.; Nesbitt, Jonathan, & Co.
    Concerning the rate of insurance on the ship "Nancy" and the impossibility of obtaining a sentence in the Court of Admiralty at Dunkirk; encloses Mr. [Richard] Gallwey's letter on this subject [2p.]; desires Franklin to lay it before the Comte de Vergennes.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 October 21; A.L.S. 1p.; Frenay, ----- Benoist de
    Forced by his singular situation to address himself to Franklin; begs for an interview.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 October 22; A.L.S. 1p.; Schaffer, John. Paris
    The bearer will convince Franklin of his intention to quit Paris and return to his own home whenever Franklin thinks proper; is ready to furnish every security in his power, if Franklin will grant him what he craves.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 October 22; N. in 3d P. 1p.; Le Veillard, Geneviève-Elisabeth Belamy
    Wishing Franklin good-morning and begging him to drink tea with her that evening.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 October 22; A.L.S. 2p.; Giordana, François. Turin
    Repeats his request of the 3d ult., and begs for a reply.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 October 23; A.L.S. 1p.; Contrepont, -----, chevalier de
    Begs for an interview on a subject he believes will give pleasure to Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 October 23; A.L.S. 3p.; Curwen, John. Little Broughton
    Though an Englishman, wished well to the Americans in their late noble struggle, and now desires to settle with his family in that country; begs for some information concerning the sale of lands and the treatment likely to be accorded them as English people.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 October 24; N. in 3d P. 1p.; Scrope, Richard
    Promising to dine with Franklin, together with Mrs. Scrope and his daughter, on the following Sunday.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 October 25; A.L.S. 4p.; Tugny, -----, chevalier de
    His plan for recruiting a body of troops for the service of America; his military experience and reputation.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 October 27; A.L.S. 2p.; Nesbitt, Jonathan, & Co.
    Enclosing a copy of the Comte de Vergennes's letter [1p]; extremely surprised at finding his sentiments on the 22d Article of the Preliminary Treaty so diametrically opposed to those of Franklin and the British Ministry; begs him to speak to the Count on the subject; if he persists in his opinion,it will be more prudent for them to abandon their dispute with the underwriters.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 October 27; A.L.S. 1p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Enclosing a letter just arrived from Philadelphia.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 October 28; A.L.S. 3p.; Newenham, Sir Edward. Dublin
    Desiring to know by return of post whether Ireland is mentioned in the Treaty; thinks Franklin is warranted in demanding this information of Mr. [David] Hartley; various ways of evading this question which the Ministry will find; public expectation high and Dublin in a state of the greatest anxiety; the dependence he puts on Franklin's assistance. Mr. [John] Foster's bill to facilitate the commercial relations between Ireland and America. Question of the protective duties will occasion much contest. Violent altercation between Mr. [Henry] Flood and Mr. [Henry] Grattan.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 October 28; A.L.S. 1p.; Birckel, -------. Strasbourg
    Refers to Franklin's letter in which he spoke of a method; this method is engraven on the soul of Franklin and on that of the best patriot in France, England and America; flight of fancy concerning the result of a union of these souls.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 October 28; A.L.S. 1p.; La Brosse, ----- du Tremblay, comtesse de
    A year ago sent Franklin a letter for her brother in Virginia; not hearing from him since, takes the liberty of enclosing another, which she begs may be sent by the first opportunity; her mother's distress at not hearing from her son.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 October 29; A.L.S. 1p.; Sutter, -----. Paris
    Report of Franklin's plan to establish, in Philadelphia, master workers in glass; offers his services as well as those of many of his associates.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 October 29; A.L.S. 2p.; Caffiéri, Jean Jacques
    Repeating his desire to execute any monuments or statues for the United States; refers to his likeness of Franklin and to the tomb of Montgomery; has the cast of Franklin's portrait in case anyone desires it.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 October 29; A.L.S. 2p.; Caffiéri, Jean Jacques
    Report that the United States intends erecting a statue to Gen. Washington; if this is true, hopes he may obtain the commission.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 October 30; A.L.S. 1p.; Hodgson, William. London
    Question of accounts and the balance due Franklin. If Congress should appoint a Consul for Great Britain, offers his services.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 October 30; A.L.S. 2p.; Schaffer, John. Paris
    Informed by his advocate of Franklin's promise to intercede with Mr. [Thomas] Barclay on his behalf. When arrested, the Inspector of Police left a man in his house to guard his goods; this person stole all that was left but he was arrested and is now in prison; begs Franklin's aid in the prosecution of this villain.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 October 30; L.S. 2p.; Lenoir, Jean-Charles-Pierre. Paris
    Concerning a young negro slave, Abigail, belonging to Mrs. Jay, who was arrested at Franklin's and her mistress's request; her unwillingness to return to her mistress; as she has no money, supposes Mrs. Jay will pay six sols a day for her food during her detention.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 October 31; A.L.S. 3p.; Vaughan, William. London
    His family's safe arrival at Philadelphia; their enjoyment of Mrs. [Richard] Bache's hospitality; her resemblance to Mrs. [Joseph] Priestley. Quotes from a letter of Miss [S.] Beckwith in which she mentions having two of Franklin's granddaughters in her house. Letters from Philadelphia speak of the displeasure occasioned by the English declaration of July 2d; laments the short-sighted policy of England. Dr. [Richard] Price communicated Franklin's description of the air balloons to the Club; is to give Dr. Price a meeting with Messrs. Jay and Adams; wishes Franklin could be present.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 October 31; A.L.S. 1p.; Schaffer, John. Paris
    Promising to repay Franklin's small advances before he leaves the country; desires a further loan of two louis in order to take the necessary steps against the person who stole his goods and clothes.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 October 31; A.L.S. 1p.; Rufin, Bernard. Passy
    Recommending two strangers to Franklin's kindness, one a linguist, capable of fulfilling the duties of a house-steward, the other a printer; their wish to dedicate their talents to America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 October; Printed 1p.; Brillon, Mme
    Announcement of their daughter's marriage to M. Paris.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1783. October.]; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Crillon, Duc and Duchesse de
    Requesting his presence at an entertainment followed by supper in honor of the birth of the two Royal children of Spain.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 November 1; A.L.S. 7p.; Boudinot, Elias. Princeton
    Refers to his last letters, enclosing the Ratification of the Treaty with Sweden and an Act of Congress for altering a few words in it. Arrival from Germany of the Baron de Beelen Bertholf and a Mr. De Boor, relative to a connection between their country and America; encloses the answer of Congress with a copy for himself. The plan of the Peace Establishment does not yet permit him to give the required information about the dismission of Franklin's grandson; Franklin's enemies too few to prevent or delay America's gratitude. Probability of their employing two or three Ministers in Europe just as residents, leaving the other business to Consuls; economical measures necessary. Acknowledging the receipt of the medals; their distribution. Results of Franklin's approbation of the Rev. [Thomas] Wren's conduct. Expects to leave the Chair of Congress the next week and return to private life at Elizabethtown. Treaty of Denmark under consideration.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 November 2; A.L.S. 1p.; Strange, Isabella. London
    A packet for her friend, Mr. [James] Hunter, of [Richmond,] Virginia; hopes he will soon tell her how to forward her letters without imposing on his kindness.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 November 3; A.L.S. 1p.; Pierres, Philippe Denis
    Sending the copies of which he spoke, also an attempt to print in gold; eager to inform Franklin of every step in his career.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 November 4; A.L.S. 2p.; Bondfield, John. Bordeaux
    Confined to his room by a broken arm, caused by a fall from his horse; will attend to Franklin's inquiries as soon as he is able. Question of allowing American merchants admission to the islands belonging to France; jealous of their sugar trade.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 November 4; L.S. 1p.; Brunville, ----- de Flaudre de. Paris
    Acceding to Franklin's request to delay judgment in the case of M. [John] Schaffer, until Mr. [Thomas] Barclay's return from Nantes.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 November 4; A.L.S. 3p.; Barthold, A. and C. Vaucher
    Their desire to live under the flag of freedom; begging for a free passage.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 November 4; L.S. 3p.; Dessin, Pierre. Calais
    Arrival of a large packet for Franklin which he will forward by the diligence; amount due him for expenses incurred.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 November 4; A.L.S. 2p.; Lavallée, N. Orleans
    Desiring to furnish America with a quantity of iron.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 November 4; A.L.S. 1p.; Lamy, -----. Paris
    Begging Franklin to accept a copy of his work in which he has been fortunate enough to place the name of Washington.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 November 4; A.L.S. 2p.; Nirmont, -----. Paris
    His unfortunate situation without money or work; begs Franklin to procure him some employment in America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 November 5; A.L.S. 2p.; Bache, Richard. Philadelphia
    Is sending two barrels of Newtown pippins, one barrel of chestnuts, a box of seeds and one of grafts; could not get a barrel of hickory nuts. Enclosing newspapers which will inform him of the unsettled state of their great folks who have been resolving and re-resolving on places for their permanent residence; they have lowered themselves much in the opinion of Americans.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 November 5; A.L.S. 1p.; Schaffer, John. Paris
    Thanking him for his offer to make him a small advance from time to time for his subsistence during his confinement; acknowledging his kindness in writing a few lines on his behalf to the King's Attorney.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 November 6; A.L.S. 2p.; Alexander, William. Nantes
    Acknowledging Franklin's favor of the 2d inst., covering a packet for the President of Congress; the two letters from a woman calling herself the widow of Mr. Sproul of Norfolk he leaves with Mr. [Jonathan] Williams [Jr.] to be returned if asked for; she is a bad woman with no mean talents of insinuation. Thanking Franklin for the recommendation to his friends; begs for a line to Mr. [Robert] Morris; expects to sail in two days.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 November 6; L.S. 3p.; Esmangare, -----. Paris
    Gives the desired information about the sailor, John Hammon; no proof of certain of his statements, but his conduct while in prison has been excellent; thinks it would be desirable to procure him a passage to America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 November 6; A.L.S. 1p.; Aleume, -----. Paris
    Begs him to authenticate two powers of attorney.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 November 8; L.S. 1p.; Cadet de Vaux, Antoine-Alexis. Paris
    Reminding Franklin of his promise to dine with him on the 12th, the day for their public meeting of the Academy.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 November 8; A.L.S. 2p.; Lacour, -----. La Rochelle
    His work in painting and faience; offers his services to the United States; question of his probable reception in America; hopes of forming an establishment there.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 November 8; A.L.S. 2p.; Houdon, Jean Antoine. Paris
    Concerning the book1 relative to the casting of the statue of Louis XV, which M. Buf[f]on proposed to deliver to Franklin; offers his own copy, in case there may be some delay in obtaining the other.
    1 Description des travaux qui ont précédé, accompagné et suivi la fonte en bronze d'un seul jet de la statue équestre de Louis XV. Dressée sur les mémoires de M. Lempereur, par M. Mariette, Paris, 1768.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 November 9; A.L.S. 3p.; Newenham, Sir Edward
    Victory for Mr. [Henry] Flood. Account of the Meeting of the Grand National Convention at the Royal Exchange; committee appointed to draw up a plan of reform; the Roman Catholics have abandoned, for the present, all pretences of obtaining votes; when Franklin has read the enclosed papers, begs him to send them to the Marquis de la Fayette.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 November 9; A.L.S. 1p.; Schaffer, John. Paris
    Reasons why he is desirous of having a trial as soon as possible.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 November 10; A.L.S. 2p.; Schaffer, John
    Urging Franklin to obtain a speedy trial for him; his health cannot stand the strain of prison life much longer.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 November 10; A.L.S. 3p.; Desfours, ----- l'aîné
    Writes again concerning a plan to make the United States a formidable rival of the European powers; will send it to him at his request.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 November 10; A.L.S. 3p.; Leidenthal, ----- de
    Believes his services will prove an acquisition to the United States; offers himself as their Minister at the Court of Saxony; enclosing a bill on the Baron d'Arendt due his friend Mr. Fritsch; asks if Franklin or some other Ambassador will undertake the payment.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 November 12; A.L.S. 3p.; Collinson, Thomas. Southgate, Middlesex
    Account of the failure of the bank and his own ruin; his present residence in a small house in the country. Talk of Philosophical subjects; Mitchell's success with his large spectrum; size of the one effected by [Sir William] Herschel; suggests some experiments on stars with a prism; the wonderful nature of light; quotes Franklin's remark that there was nothing he was so much in the dark about as light; lacks knowledge of Herschel's experiments. Kindness of Sir Joseph Banks in offering him the use of his library. Marriage of his nephew, Tritton.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 November 13; A.L.S. 1p.; Mather, Samuel. Boston
    Being in his seventy-eighth year and thinking what he could do for the benefit and comfort of his country, decided to write The Dying Legacy which he now sends to Dr. Franklin; acknowledgment of it he received from the President of Congress.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 November 13; L.S. 1p.; Lenoir, Jean-Charles-Pierre
    Sending Franklin the necessary permission to obtain his books from the custom-house.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 November 13; A.L.S. 1p.; Grandais, ----- du Demaine
    Offers the homage of a young ecclesiastic; wishes to take charge of a young person's education; likelihood of the Americans sending their children to France to be educated; hopes Franklin will aid him.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 November 14; A.L.S. 2p.; Pecoul, ------. Paris
    Concerning a debt due him by M. John Schaffer of Philadelphia, detained in the prisons of the Grand Chatelet; hears that Franklin has interested himself in this unfortunate and wishes to give his creditors their just dues; begs Franklin to take his case into consideration.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 November 15; L.S. 2p.; Rouzier, -----. Montargis
    Account of his sufferings from gout; begs Franklin to aid him in regaining his health.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 November 16; A.L.S. 1p.; Malberg, -----Carré de
    Sending a work whose plan is new although its subject is old.
    (In French).
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 November 16; L.S. 2p.; Wavran, abbé -----
    Prevented by illness from sending Franklin his works; wrote to the Marquis de Condorcet, Secretary of the Academy of Sciences, proposing a discussion as to the true theory of electricity; by the experiments he has made along Franklin's line, is convinced of the falseness of the Abbé Nollet's theory; has received no answer from the Marquis; begs the favor of Franklin's protection.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 November 17; A.L.S. 2p.; Tugny, -----, chevalier de
    Desiring to know whether his plan of the 30th ult. failed to arrive or whether it was unworthy of Franklin's approbation.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 November 17; A.L.S. 3p.; Bevage, -----, abbé Canon of Nismes
    Enclosing a letter for [Henry] Laurens and begging him to read it before sending it on; it concerns Mr. Laurens's promise to solicit a higher rank for his brother, M. de la Boyére, Captain of a Soissonais regiment.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 November 17; A.L.S. 3p.; Brown, Walter. Newcastle-upon-Tyne
    Congratulating Franklin on the glorious liberty and independence of his country, in which he had so great a hand. His plan to establish a linen manufactory in America. Is the father of twenty-one children; anxious to provide for those still under his care and also to be useful to America, where he hopes in the future to lay his bones.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 November 18; A.L.S. 5p.; Mono, Joh Georg. Hochberg near Emmendingen
    Is a Lutheran minister and the father of five children; his third son desirous of trying his fortune in foreign lands; begs Franklin to either take him into his own service or find him some position in America; as he has no money, asks that his expenses may be defrayed.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 November 19; A.L.S. 2p.; Ingenhousz, Jan
    Acknowledging Franklin's favor of Sept. 2d, 1783, with Mr. Samuel Wharton's enclosure and bill of exchange for £8,000; never received a number of Mr. Wharton's letters; gives directions how letters to Europe should be addressed. His interest in aerial balloons. Anxious to know if Franklin received his letter of August 15th. Expects his book to come out soon; M. Lavoisier's pamphlet on heat contains nothing similar to his work; has matter enough ready for a second volume of his book on vegetables; afraid of the delay in printing it. Desires to become a member of the [American] Philosophical Society of Philadelphia. Dutch hatred against England. Report of Mr. [Samuel] Wharton being in some difficulty about an immense tract of land he bought from the Indians.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 November 19; A.L.S. 1p.; Schaffer, John. Paris
    Informed by his advocate that Franklin's son, William Temple, must write a line to deny having said that he (Schaffer) was a bad subject, etc. Mr. [William] Temple [Franklin]'s refusal to do this shows he must have said it; begs Franklin to procure this favor for him and to make him a small advance.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 November 19; A.L.S. 2p.; Bancroft, Edward Nathaniel. Chiswick
    An account of their voyage to England and his father's departure for Philadelphia; his opinion of London and English food.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 November 20; A.L.S. 1p.; Cooper, Samuel. Boston
    Writes under great difficulties; ill in his room attended by two physicians; cannot allow the Chevalier de Born to depart without carrying his thanks to Franklin for introducing to him such an able and talented gentleman; when he is better, hopes to aid the Chevalier in his views in the Consular line.
    A.E. by Dr. Franklin. "The last letter from my dear friend Dr. Cooper, who died in January following."
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 November 21; A.L.S. 3p.; Born, Ignace, chevalier de
    Begging Franklin to forward the enclosed letter to Professor Märter at Philadelphia, his pupil, disciple and friend; suggested his name to the Emperor for the voyage to America, on account of his discoveries in Natural History; the bearer is M. [Paul] Strattmann sent by the Emperor to buy a part of the Duc de la Vallière's library.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 November 21; A.L.S. 1p.; Lefebvre de Revel, -----, fils
    Sent Franklin a memoir in the early part of October, concerning a request of the Neapolitan merchants for protection in the ports of the United States, where they propose to trade; begs for an answer.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 November 24; A.L.S. 2p.; St. Olympe, -----, chevalier de. Havre
    Takes advantage of his last moments in France to express his veneration and respect for Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 November 25; A.L.S. 2p.; Newenham, Sir Edward
    Results of the Grand National Convention; believes they will obtain a real reform. Desires Franklin's advice concerning a separate and distinct treaty between Ireland and the United States. Their Parliament daily sinking in the estimation of the public and with good reason; gives an account of their proceedings.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 November 25; A.L.S. 2p.; Rousseau, Jean. London
    Has heard much of the jealousy in America as to the choice of a place for the sessions of Congress; advises their not sitting permanently in one place, but alternately in each of the thirteen provinces; hopes the idea will prove useful.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 November 25; A.L.S. 4p.; Guffroy, Armand Benoit Joseph. Arras
    Concerning a request of the Chevalier du Richebourg for his share of the prize-money during his service in Commodore Jones's squadron on board the "Vengeance"; account of the fruitless efforts made by the Chevalier to obtain his just dues.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 November 27; A.L.S. 2p.; Guyon, -----
    His miserable condition; is sixty-one years old; lost his wife, after fifteen months' illness, and later his position as Receiver-General of Finances; there is still left him a little girl, an idiot; gives a minute account of the way the child was affected from infancy [2p.]; throws himself on Franklin's kindness.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 November 28; A.L.S. 2p.; Court de Gébelin, Antoine
    Sending some tickets for the meeting at the Museum on December 4; their entire Society will be most flattered by Franklin's presence; their hope of bringing out a volume of memoirs during the winter; will be glad if Franklin would contribute to this first volume. Recommending his friend, M. Dupuis, an architect, who wishes to dedicate to the Queen his latest work, a plan for a magnificent play-house; begs Franklin's influence in his favor with the Comte de Vaudreuil.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 November 28; A.L.S. 3p.; Menier de Saint Yver, -----
    Franklin's abandonment of M. [John] Schaffer will plunge another family into misery; has no reason to defend Schaffer, but firmly believes him the victim of others; the interpretation which will be put upon Franklin's attitude; M. Schaffer's downfall will carry him with it; begs Franklin to have pity on him and his family.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 November 28; A.L.S. 3p.; Banks, Sir Joseph. London
    Concerning [Joseph Michel] Montgolfier's experiments; account of the ascent of a balloon in Sussex.
    Printed in Works (Sparks, X, 32)
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 November 28; A.L.S. 2p.; Douglas, Katharine Sproale
    Expressions of the deepest gratitude for what Franklin has done for Miss Maxwell and for herself; hopes that she and her seven children will obtain their just claim on Virginia property.